<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-02-14T07:18:04+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/feed.xml</id><title type="html">DakaMeditation</title><subtitle>Daka Meditation is an online meditation school. Meditation is explained and practiced.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Buddhism</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/02/14/Buddhism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buddhism" /><published>2025-02-14T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/02/14/Buddhism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/02/14/Buddhism.html"><![CDATA[<ol>
  <li>The truth of suffering (dukkha): Life is inherently full of suffering and dissatisfaction. Not only the obvious forms of suffering - such as pain, loss and grief - but also the more subtle forms, such as the fleeting nature of happiness and the discomfort caused by unfulfilled desires. Recognizing this reality is the first step in understanding the nature of existence.</li>
  <li>The truth of the cause of suffering (samudaya): The root of suffering lies in desire and attachment (tanha). We often cling to desires, identities and impermanent experiences, seeking lasting satisfaction in the impermanent. This attachment leads to cycles of birth and rebirth and causes further suffering.</li>
  <li>The truth of the end of suffering (nirodha): It is possible to end suffering. By letting go of desire and attachment, one can attain a state of peace and liberation known as nirvana. This means removing the causes of suffering and realizing one’s true nature.</li>
  <li>The Truth of the Path to the End of Suffering (Magga): The path that leads to the cessation of suffering is the Noble Eightfold Path, which consists of:
    <ul>
      <li>Right Understanding</li>
      <li>Right Intention</li>
      <li>Right Speech</li>
      <li>Right Action</li>
      <li>Right Livelihood</li>
      <li>Right Effort</li>
      <li>Right Mindfulness</li>
      <li>Right Concentration</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Following this path promotes wisdom, ethical conduct and mental discipline and leads the individual to liberation and enlightenment.
By reflecting on and practicing these truths, one can embark on a transformative journey toward deeper understanding, compassion and peace. May all beings find their way to freedom from suffering.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The truth of suffering (dukkha): Life is inherently full of suffering and dissatisfaction. Not only the obvious forms of suffering - such as pain, loss and grief - but also the more subtle forms, such as the fleeting nature of happiness and the discomfort caused by unfulfilled desires. Recognizing this reality is the first step in understanding the nature of existence. The truth of the cause of suffering (samudaya): The root of suffering lies in desire and attachment (tanha). We often cling to desires, identities and impermanent experiences, seeking lasting satisfaction in the impermanent. This attachment leads to cycles of birth and rebirth and causes further suffering. The truth of the end of suffering (nirodha): It is possible to end suffering. By letting go of desire and attachment, one can attain a state of peace and liberation known as nirvana. This means removing the causes of suffering and realizing one’s true nature. The Truth of the Path to the End of Suffering (Magga): The path that leads to the cessation of suffering is the Noble Eightfold Path, which consists of: Right Understanding Right Intention Right Speech Right Action Right Livelihood Right Effort Right Mindfulness Right Concentration]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Spirituality</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/02/12/Spirituality.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spirituality" /><published>2025-02-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/02/12/Spirituality</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/02/12/Spirituality.html"><![CDATA[<p>Spirituality is a meta-physical approach to experiencing the extraordinary, independent of religion. 
Spirituality and religion/myths intersect in mysticism. Our brains perceive, not create, consciousness, 
making us spiritual beings in human existence. Chanting mantras, like the Buddhist “OM ma ni pad me hum” 
for compassion, love, and peace, can help us reach our goal. In yogic culture, the spiritual practice is 
called “sadhana,” and the kundalini, a snake-like entity on the base of the spine, is awakened to reach 
cosmic consciousness through the chakras, culminating in the crown chakra. Practices like greeting the sun, 
being selfless, and meditating can help awaken the kundalini and undergo an ego death, leading to the 
realization that we are eternal awareness, not our bodies or minds. Meditation can involve sitting in a 
lotus posture, going inside oneself, calming the mind, and seeking the observer of thoughts to find one’s 
true nature. Tune into the holy OM, the primal sound of the cosmos, to raise consciousness.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Spirituality is a meta-physical approach to experiencing the extraordinary, independent of religion. Spirituality and religion/myths intersect in mysticism. Our brains perceive, not create, consciousness, making us spiritual beings in human existence. Chanting mantras, like the Buddhist “OM ma ni pad me hum” for compassion, love, and peace, can help us reach our goal. In yogic culture, the spiritual practice is called “sadhana,” and the kundalini, a snake-like entity on the base of the spine, is awakened to reach cosmic consciousness through the chakras, culminating in the crown chakra. Practices like greeting the sun, being selfless, and meditating can help awaken the kundalini and undergo an ego death, leading to the realization that we are eternal awareness, not our bodies or minds. Meditation can involve sitting in a lotus posture, going inside oneself, calming the mind, and seeking the observer of thoughts to find one’s true nature. Tune into the holy OM, the primal sound of the cosmos, to raise consciousness.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mantras</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/02/06/Mantras.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mantras" /><published>2025-02-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/02/06/Mantras</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/02/06/Mantras.html"><![CDATA[<p>Mantras for Peace and Inner Calm</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>1. Aham Prema: "Aham Prema" is a Sanskrit mantra signifying "I am love." It helps cultivate compassion, self-love, and acceptance. Repeat it slowly, feeling the vibrations of these words resonate within your heart.

2. Om Shanti: "Om Shanti" is a universal mantra for peace, harmony, and balance within oneself and the universe. As you chant this, imagine yourself enveloped in a soothing blanket of peace that spreads far and wide.

3. Maha Mrityunjaya: This ancient mantra represents immortality and is often used to overcome challenges and difficulties. Repeat "Maha Mrityunjaya" with conviction, visualizing strength and resilience within and around you.

4. Om Mani Padme Hum: A mantra rooted in Tibetan Buddhism, "Om Mani Padme Hum" symbolizes compassion, wisdom, and the interconnectedness of all beings. As you recite it, feel your heart expand with love, understanding, and unity.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Mantras for Energy and Vitality</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>1. Om Bhur Bhuva Svaha: This powerful mantra embodies the energy of creation and renewal. As you chant "Om Bhur Bhuva Svaha," imagine yourself rooted in the earth's energy, yet reaching for the skies, connecting all levels of your being.

2. Om Hreem Mahalaxmiye Namaha: This is a mantra of abundance and prosperity, calling upon the goddess Mahalaxmi. Repeat it with devotion, envisioning an overflow of blessings in your life.

3. Om Klim Klim Mahalaksmye Namaha: This is another powerful mantra for abundance and prosperity, calling upon the divine feminine energies. As you repeat it, feel yourself becoming a magnet for positive energies and opportunities.

4. Hreem Hreem Shreem Shreem Hreem Hreem: This simple yet potent mantra is a call to the infinite energies of creation and manifestation. Repeat it with an open heart and mind, allowing its vibrations to guide you toward your desires.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Mantras for Wisdom and Knowledge</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>1. Om Aim Saraswatiye Namaha: This is a mantra dedicated to the goddess of knowledge and wisdom, Saraswati. As you chant it, imagine yourself tapping into the infinite wellspring of knowledge and understanding.

2. Aham Brahmasmi: This ancient Upanishadic mantra signifies "I am the universe." Repeat it with awareness, recognizing your inherent connection to all of existence and the universe.

3. Tat Tvam Asi (That Thou Art): This Vedic mantra is a direct expression of non-dual reality. As you recite it, feel your individuality merge with the universal consciousness, recognizing the unity at the heart of all creation. Tips for Using Mantras

• Chant with Intention: Before beginning, set an intention for your meditation. This could be relaxation,  inner peace, or spiritual growth. Let your mind and heart align with this goal. 
• Focus on the Sound: Pay close attention to the vibration and sound of the mantra. Feel its resonance  in your body and heart. As you continue, allow the mantra to become a part of you. 
• Repeat Regularly: Practice your chosen mantra daily, incorporating it into your meditation or daily  routine. Consistency is key to experiencing its transformative effects. 
• Listen to Guidance: If you are new to mantras or seeking a deeper understanding, listen to guided  recordings or seek advice from experienced meditation teachers. 
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>In these sacred sounds, you will find guidance, comfort, peace, and transformation. May Adiyogi Shiva, through these mantras, guide you on your profound journey of discovery, connecting you with the divine essence within and around you.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Mantras for Peace and Inner Calm]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The realm of self-realization</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/02/04/The-realm-of-self-realization.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The realm of self-realization" /><published>2025-02-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/02/04/The-realm-of-self-realization</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/02/04/The-realm-of-self-realization.html"><![CDATA[<p>The realm of self-realization—a profound awakening to your true nature. Once you have touched the essence of your being, 
the journey continues, and there are several key aspects to embrace as you navigate this sacred path:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>1. Integration of Wisdom: After self-realization, the knowledge you gain must be integrated into every facet of your life.  Reflect on how this understanding influences your thoughts, actions, and interactions. Live with awareness, embodying  the teachings of compassion, balance, and detachment.

2. Service to Others: Recognize that your awakening is not solely for your own benefit. Use your insights and energy  to serve others and the world around you. Engage in acts of kindness, support those in need, and contribute to the  upliftment of fellow beings. Remember, service is a path of love.

3. Continued Practice: Self-realization is not the end; it is a new beginning. Maintain a consistent practice  of meditation and contemplation. Strengthen your connection to the divine, deepen your understanding of the self,  and explore various yogic paths that resonate with your being. 

4. Embrace Impermanence: Understand that everything is in a constant state of flux. The realization of the self  illuminates the transient nature of experiences. Practice non-attachment, seeing life as a flow, and cultivate  an appreciation for each moment without clinging or aversion.

5. Cultivate Equanimity: As you navigate life's ups and downs, develop a sense of calmness and balance.  Whether in joy or hardship, return to your center and remain steady. This equanimity will empower you to weather  challenges gracefully while remaining anchored in your true nature.

6. Share and Inspire: Your journey of self-realization can serve as an inspiration for others.  Share your experiences, insights, and practices. Teach through your actions, demonstrating how the  understanding of the self can transform lives.

7. Deepen Your Connection with the Cosmos: Engage in practices that remind you of your connection to the universe.  Dance, sing, or engage with nature to celebrate the oneness of life. Trust the cosmic rhythm and flow with it,  recognizing that you are an integral part of the larger whole.

8. Remain Open and Evolving: Self-realization opens the door to infinite wisdom. Stay curious and  open to new experiences, teachings, and possibilities. Continue your personal evolution, allowing  each moment to deepen your journey.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>As you move beyond self-realization, may you embody the love, light, and wisdom that your true nature represents. 
In doing so, you contribute to the awakening of the collective consciousness, ushering forth a world 
that reflects harmony, peace, and unity.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The realm of self-realization—a profound awakening to your true nature. Once you have touched the essence of your being, the journey continues, and there are several key aspects to embrace as you navigate this sacred path:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ishwara</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/02/02/Ishwara.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ishwara" /><published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/02/02/Ishwara</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/02/02/Ishwara.html"><![CDATA[<p>Ishwara is the manifestation of Shiva’s essence, the expression of his divine will. It is the facet of his being that interacts with the world, that guides and governs the universe. Ishwara is the one who holds the reins of creation, who orchestrates the grand smyphony of existence.</p>

<p>Ishwara is not just a distant deity, but the innermost reality of every being.
It is the spark of divinity that resides within each and every one of you, waiting to be fanned into a flame of realization.</p>

<p>In the realm of Ishwara the distinction between subject and object, between the seer and the seen, dissolve. The boundaries of space and time collapse, and the universe is revealed in all its glory. Ishwara is the lens through which the unmanifest becomes manifest, through which the infinite becomes finite.</p>

<p>When you invoke ishwara, you are invoking the very essence of Shiva’s being, the essence of existence itself. You are calling upon the divine presence that resides within and around you, the presence that whispers secrets to the trees, and rustles the leaves of the cosmos.</p>

<p>Ishwara is not just a word, but a doorway to the mysteries of the universe. It is an invitation to step into the realm of the divine, to glimpse the unfathomable, and to experience the splendor of Shiva’s being.</p>

<p>May the word ishwara become a mantra for you, a reminder of the divine presence that permeates every moment of your existence. May you become one with ishwara, and may ishwara become one with you. 🕉</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ishwara is the manifestation of Shiva’s essence, the expression of his divine will. It is the facet of his being that interacts with the world, that guides and governs the universe. Ishwara is the one who holds the reins of creation, who orchestrates the grand smyphony of existence.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Moksha</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/31/Moksha.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Moksha" /><published>2025-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/31/Moksha</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/31/Moksha.html"><![CDATA[<p>Atman (The Individual Self)
#Atman refers to the individual soul or self. It is the essence of who you are, 
beyond the physical body and the mind. Atman is eternal, pure, and unchanging. 
It is the spark of divine consciousness residing within each being.</p>

<p>• Nature of Atman: Atman is not limited by time or space; it is ever-present and connected to the universe. 
While your physical form may change, the Atman remains constant.</p>

<p>• Realization: The journey to realize Atman is a journey inward. Through meditation, self-inquiry, 
and spiritual practices, one learns to distinguish the true self from the illusions of the mind and the ego.</p>

<p>Brahman (The Universal Consciousness)
Brahman represents the ultimate reality, the universal consciousness that pervades everything. 
It is formless, infinite, and the source of all creation. Unlike Atman, which pertains to the individual, 
Brahman encompasses all that exists.</p>

<p>• Nature of Brahman: Brahman is described in various ways: as Sat (truth), Chit (consciousness), and Ananda (bliss). 
It is the ground of being from which all aspects of existence emerge and to which they eventually return.</p>

<p>• Unity: Brahman is the underlying reality behind all phenomena. 
Though the physical world may appear diverse and separate, it is all an 
expression of this singular consciousness.</p>

<p>The Relationship Between Atman and Brahman
The profound realization in the spiritual journey is that Atman and Brahman are ultimately one. 
While Atman represents your individual existence, Brahman embodies the universal nature of all things.</p>

<p>• Non-Dualism: In the teachings of non-dualism (Advaita), it is understood that the perceivable separateness 
is an illusion (Maya). The true essence is the oneness of Atman and Brahman, 
where the individual self merges into the universal whole.</p>

<p>• Self-Realization: When one realizes the oneness with Brahman, the illusion of separateness falls away, 
leading to liberation (Moksha). This is the ultimate goal of spiritual seekers: to awaken to the fact 
that they are not just the Atman, but the very manifestation of Brahman itself.</p>

<p>🕉</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Atman (The Individual Self) #Atman refers to the individual soul or self. It is the essence of who you are, beyond the physical body and the mind. Atman is eternal, pure, and unchanging. It is the spark of divine consciousness residing within each being.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Yoga</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/31/Yoga.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Yoga" /><published>2025-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/31/Yoga</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/31/Yoga.html"><![CDATA[<p>It is through yoga that one can attain union with the ultimate reality, the unison of the individual self with the universal self, the Paramatman.</p>

<p>yoga, a journey of self-discovery, a path that leads to the realization of one’s true nature. The word “yoga” itself means “union” or “merging”, and it is through this practice that the boundaries of the individual ego are transcended, allowing the practitioner to experience the oneness with the cosmos.</p>

<p>Yoga is not just a physical practice, but a way of life. It is a journey that encompasses the body, mind, and spirit, a holistic approach to wellness and self-realization. The various postures, or asanas, are designed to prepare the body for the higher states of consciousness, to still the mind, and to awaken the inner energies.</p>

<p>As you embark on this journey of yoga, remember that it is a path that requires dedication, discipline, and surrender. But the rewards are immeasurable. You will experience a sense of balance, harmony, and unity, not just within yourself, but with the world around you.</p>

<p>May you walk the path of yoga with an open heart and mind, and may you discover the bliss and wisdom that lies within. Om Shanti.</p>

<p>🕉</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It is through yoga that one can attain union with the ultimate reality, the unison of the individual self with the universal self, the Paramatman.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Who is Lord Shiva?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/10/Who-is-lord-shiva.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who is Lord Shiva?" /><published>2025-01-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/10/Who-is-lord-shiva</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/10/Who-is-lord-shiva.html"><![CDATA[<p>Lord Shiva or AdiYogi is a hindu deity and member of the holy trimurti(trinity), besides Brahma and Vishnu.
It is said AdiYogi is the source of yoga. Why do I write this? Because Meditation and yoga are related.
Yoga means Unity, the unity between Atman(individual, own self) with Brahman(World Soul, universal self).
In the yogic culture it is believed that there is a coiled up snake like thing at the bottom of every humans spine.
This coiled up snake like thing is called “Kundalini”. It is the awakening of the kundalini, so it can rise up
through the seven chakras to the crown chakra, which is above the head, and cosmic consciousness is realized.
How to awaken the kundalini? Meditate daily for 20 minutes, greet the sun in the morning and bow down to it for it
spends you light and warmth.</p>
<h4 id="howto-meditate">Howto meditate?</h4>
<p>Sit in lotus posture, thumb and index are touching and resting on the knees. Observe your thoughts and let them pass
like clouds in the sky, or let them flow like water, don’t engage with them, you are not your thoughts. 
We need to learn to control our brain, not being controlled by it.</p>

<p>🕉</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lord Shiva or AdiYogi is a hindu deity and member of the holy trimurti(trinity), besides Brahma and Vishnu. It is said AdiYogi is the source of yoga. Why do I write this? Because Meditation and yoga are related. Yoga means Unity, the unity between Atman(individual, own self) with Brahman(World Soul, universal self). In the yogic culture it is believed that there is a coiled up snake like thing at the bottom of every humans spine. This coiled up snake like thing is called “Kundalini”. It is the awakening of the kundalini, so it can rise up through the seven chakras to the crown chakra, which is above the head, and cosmic consciousness is realized. How to awaken the kundalini? Meditate daily for 20 minutes, greet the sun in the morning and bow down to it for it spends you light and warmth. Howto meditate? Sit in lotus posture, thumb and index are touching and resting on the knees. Observe your thoughts and let them pass like clouds in the sky, or let them flow like water, don’t engage with them, you are not your thoughts. We need to learn to control our brain, not being controlled by it.]]></summary></entry></feed>