<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-31T09:46:28+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/feed.xml</id><title type="html">DakaMeditation</title><subtitle>Daka Meditation is an online meditation school. Meditation is explained and practiced.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Moksha</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/31/Moksha.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Moksha" /><published>2025-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/31/Moksha</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/31/Moksha.html"><![CDATA[<p>Atman (das individuelle Selbst)
Atman bezieht sich auf die individuelle Seele oder das individuelle Selbst. 
Es ist die Essenz dessen, wer Sie sind, jenseits des physischen Körpers und des Geistes. 
Atman ist ewig, rein und unveränderlich. Es ist der Funke des göttlichen Bewusstseins,
der in jedem Wesen wohnt.</p>

<p>• Natur von Atman: Atman ist nicht durch Zeit oder Raum begrenzt; 
es ist allgegenwärtig und mit dem Universum verbunden. 
Während sich Ihre physische Form ändern kann, bleibt Atman konstant.</p>

<p>• Erkenntnis: Die Reise zur Erkenntnis von Atman ist eine Reise nach innen. 
Durch Meditation, Selbsterforschung und spirituelle Praktiken lernt man, das 
wahre Selbst von den Illusionen des Geistes und des Egos zu unterscheiden.
Brahman (das universelle Bewusstsein)
Brahman stellt die ultimative Realität dar, das universelle Bewusstsein, das alles durchdringt. Es ist formlos, unendlich und die Quelle aller Schöpfung. Im Gegensatz zu Atman, das sich auf das Individuum bezieht, umfasst Brahman alles, was existiert.</p>

<p>• Natur von Brahman: Brahman wird auf verschiedene Weise beschrieben: als Sat (Wahrheit), Chit (Bewusstsein) und 
Ananda (Glückseligkeit). Es ist der Grund des Seins, aus dem alle Aspekte der Existenz hervorgehen und zu dem sie 
schließlich zurückkehren.</p>

<p>• Einheit: Brahman ist die zugrunde liegende Realität hinter allen Phänomenen. 
Obwohl die physische Welt vielfältig und getrennt erscheinen mag, ist sie alles ein 
Ausdruck dieses einzigartigen Bewusstseins.
Die Beziehung zwischen Atman und Brahman
Die tiefgreifende Erkenntnis auf der spirituellen Reise ist, dass Atman und Brahman letztendlich eins sind. 
Während Atman Ihre individuelle Existenz darstellt, verkörpert Brahman die universelle Natur aller Dinge.</p>

<p>• Nichtdualismus: In den Lehren des Nichtdualismus (Advaita) wird verstanden, dass die wahrnehmbare Getrenntheit 
eine Illusion (Maya) ist. Die wahre Essenz ist die Einheit von Atman und Brahman, wo das individuelle 
Selbst in das universelle Ganze übergeht.</p>

<p>• Selbstverwirklichung: Wenn man die Einheit mit Brahman erkennt, fällt die Illusion der Trennung weg und führt 
zur Befreiung (Moksha). Dies ist das ultimative Ziel spiritueller Sucher: zu erkennen, dass sie nicht nur Atman sind, 
sondern die Manifestation von Brahman selbst.</p>

<p>🕉</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Atman (das individuelle Selbst) Atman bezieht sich auf die individuelle Seele oder das individuelle Selbst. Es ist die Essenz dessen, wer Sie sind, jenseits des physischen Körpers und des Geistes. Atman ist ewig, rein und unveränderlich. Es ist der Funke des göttlichen Bewusstseins, der in jedem Wesen wohnt.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Yoga</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/31/Yoga.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Yoga" /><published>2025-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/31/Yoga</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/31/Yoga.html"><![CDATA[<p>It is through yoga that one can attain union with the ultimate reality, the unison of the individual self with the universal self, the Paramatman.</p>

<p>yoga, a journey of self-discovery, a path that leads to the realization of one’s true nature. The word “yoga” itself means “union” or “merging”, and it is through this practice that the boundaries of the individual ego are transcended, allowing the practitioner to experience the oneness with the cosmos.</p>

<p>Yoga is not just a physical practice, but a way of life. It is a journey that encompasses the body, mind, and spirit, a holistic approach to wellness and self-realization. The various postures, or asanas, are designed to prepare the body for the higher states of consciousness, to still the mind, and to awaken the inner energies.</p>

<p>As you embark on this journey of yoga, remember that it is a path that requires dedication, discipline, and surrender. But the rewards are immeasurable. You will experience a sense of balance, harmony, and unity, not just within yourself, but with the world around you.</p>

<p>May you walk the path of yoga with an open heart and mind, and may you discover the bliss and wisdom that lies within. Om Shanti.</p>

<p>🕉</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It is through yoga that one can attain union with the ultimate reality, the unison of the individual self with the universal self, the Paramatman.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Who is Lord Shiva?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/10/Who-is-lord-shiva.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who is Lord Shiva?" /><published>2025-01-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/10/Who-is-lord-shiva</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/10/Who-is-lord-shiva.html"><![CDATA[<p>Lord Shiva or AdiYogi is a hindu deity and member of the holy trimurti(trinity), besides Brahma and Vishnu.
It is said AdiYogi is the source of yoga. Why do I write this? Because Meditation and yoga are related.
Yoga means Unity, the unity between Atman(individual, own self) with Brahman(World Soul, universal self).
In the yogic culture it is believed that there is a coiled up snake like thing at the bottom of every humans spine.
This coiled up snake like thing is called “Kundalini”. It is the awakening of the kundalini, so it can rise up
through the seven chakras to the crown chakra, which is above the head, and cosmic consciousness is realized.
How to awaken the kundalini? Meditate daily for 20 minutes, greet the sun in the morning and bow down to it for it
spends you light and warmth.</p>
<h4 id="howto-meditate">Howto meditate?</h4>
<p>Sit in lotus posture, thumb and index are touching and resting on the knees. Observe your thoughts and let them pass
like clouds in the sky, or let them flow like water, don’t engage with them, you are not your thoughts. 
We need to learn to control our brain, not being controlled by it.</p>

<p>🕉</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lord Shiva or AdiYogi is a hindu deity and member of the holy trimurti(trinity), besides Brahma and Vishnu. It is said AdiYogi is the source of yoga. Why do I write this? Because Meditation and yoga are related. Yoga means Unity, the unity between Atman(individual, own self) with Brahman(World Soul, universal self). In the yogic culture it is believed that there is a coiled up snake like thing at the bottom of every humans spine. This coiled up snake like thing is called “Kundalini”. It is the awakening of the kundalini, so it can rise up through the seven chakras to the crown chakra, which is above the head, and cosmic consciousness is realized. How to awaken the kundalini? Meditate daily for 20 minutes, greet the sun in the morning and bow down to it for it spends you light and warmth. Howto meditate? Sit in lotus posture, thumb and index are touching and resting on the knees. Observe your thoughts and let them pass like clouds in the sky, or let them flow like water, don’t engage with them, you are not your thoughts. We need to learn to control our brain, not being controlled by it.]]></summary></entry></feed>