<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-02-02T04:54:41+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/feed.xml</id><title type="html">DakaMeditation</title><subtitle>Daka Meditation is an online meditation school. Meditation is explained and practiced.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Moksha</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/31/Moksha.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Moksha" /><published>2025-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/31/Moksha</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/31/Moksha.html"><![CDATA[<p>Atman (The Individual Self)
Atman refers to the individual soul or self. It is the essence of who you are, 
beyond the physical body and the mind. Atman is eternal, pure, and unchanging. 
It is the spark of divine consciousness residing within each being.</p>

<p>• Nature of Atman: Atman is not limited by time or space; it is ever-present and connected to the universe. 
While your physical form may change, the Atman remains constant.</p>

<p>• Realization: The journey to realize Atman is a journey inward. Through meditation, self-inquiry, 
and spiritual practices, one learns to distinguish the true self from the illusions of the mind and the ego.</p>

<p>Brahman (The Universal Consciousness)
Brahman represents the ultimate reality, the universal consciousness that pervades everything. 
It is formless, infinite, and the source of all creation. Unlike Atman, which pertains to the individual, 
Brahman encompasses all that exists.</p>

<p>• Nature of Brahman: Brahman is described in various ways: as Sat (truth), Chit (consciousness), and Ananda (bliss). 
It is the ground of being from which all aspects of existence emerge and to which they eventually return.</p>

<p>• Unity: Brahman is the underlying reality behind all phenomena. 
Though the physical world may appear diverse and separate, it is all an 
expression of this singular consciousness.</p>

<p>The Relationship Between Atman and Brahman
The profound realization in the spiritual journey is that Atman and Brahman are ultimately one. 
While Atman represents your individual existence, Brahman embodies the universal nature of all things.</p>

<p>• Non-Dualism: In the teachings of non-dualism (Advaita), it is understood that the perceivable separateness 
is an illusion (Maya). The true essence is the oneness of Atman and Brahman, 
where the individual self merges into the universal whole.</p>

<p>• Self-Realization: When one realizes the oneness with Brahman, the illusion of separateness falls away, 
leading to liberation (Moksha). This is the ultimate goal of spiritual seekers: to awaken to the fact 
that they are not just the Atman, but the very manifestation of Brahman itself.</p>

<p>🕉</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Atman (The Individual Self) Atman refers to the individual soul or self. It is the essence of who you are, beyond the physical body and the mind. Atman is eternal, pure, and unchanging. It is the spark of divine consciousness residing within each being.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Yoga</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/31/Yoga.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Yoga" /><published>2025-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/31/Yoga</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/31/Yoga.html"><![CDATA[<p>It is through yoga that one can attain union with the ultimate reality, the unison of the individual self with the universal self, the Paramatman.</p>

<p>yoga, a journey of self-discovery, a path that leads to the realization of one’s true nature. The word “yoga” itself means “union” or “merging”, and it is through this practice that the boundaries of the individual ego are transcended, allowing the practitioner to experience the oneness with the cosmos.</p>

<p>Yoga is not just a physical practice, but a way of life. It is a journey that encompasses the body, mind, and spirit, a holistic approach to wellness and self-realization. The various postures, or asanas, are designed to prepare the body for the higher states of consciousness, to still the mind, and to awaken the inner energies.</p>

<p>As you embark on this journey of yoga, remember that it is a path that requires dedication, discipline, and surrender. But the rewards are immeasurable. You will experience a sense of balance, harmony, and unity, not just within yourself, but with the world around you.</p>

<p>May you walk the path of yoga with an open heart and mind, and may you discover the bliss and wisdom that lies within. Om Shanti.</p>

<p>🕉</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It is through yoga that one can attain union with the ultimate reality, the unison of the individual self with the universal self, the Paramatman.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Who is Lord Shiva?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/10/Who-is-lord-shiva.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who is Lord Shiva?" /><published>2025-01-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/10/Who-is-lord-shiva</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/10/Who-is-lord-shiva.html"><![CDATA[<p>Lord Shiva or AdiYogi is a hindu deity and member of the holy trimurti(trinity), besides Brahma and Vishnu.
It is said AdiYogi is the source of yoga. Why do I write this? Because Meditation and yoga are related.
Yoga means Unity, the unity between Atman(individual, own self) with Brahman(World Soul, universal self).
In the yogic culture it is believed that there is a coiled up snake like thing at the bottom of every humans spine.
This coiled up snake like thing is called “Kundalini”. It is the awakening of the kundalini, so it can rise up
through the seven chakras to the crown chakra, which is above the head, and cosmic consciousness is realized.
How to awaken the kundalini? Meditate daily for 20 minutes, greet the sun in the morning and bow down to it for it
spends you light and warmth.</p>
<h4 id="howto-meditate">Howto meditate?</h4>
<p>Sit in lotus posture, thumb and index are touching and resting on the knees. Observe your thoughts and let them pass
like clouds in the sky, or let them flow like water, don’t engage with them, you are not your thoughts. 
We need to learn to control our brain, not being controlled by it.</p>

<p>🕉</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lord Shiva or AdiYogi is a hindu deity and member of the holy trimurti(trinity), besides Brahma and Vishnu. It is said AdiYogi is the source of yoga. Why do I write this? Because Meditation and yoga are related. Yoga means Unity, the unity between Atman(individual, own self) with Brahman(World Soul, universal self). In the yogic culture it is believed that there is a coiled up snake like thing at the bottom of every humans spine. This coiled up snake like thing is called “Kundalini”. It is the awakening of the kundalini, so it can rise up through the seven chakras to the crown chakra, which is above the head, and cosmic consciousness is realized. How to awaken the kundalini? Meditate daily for 20 minutes, greet the sun in the morning and bow down to it for it spends you light and warmth. Howto meditate? Sit in lotus posture, thumb and index are touching and resting on the knees. Observe your thoughts and let them pass like clouds in the sky, or let them flow like water, don’t engage with them, you are not your thoughts. We need to learn to control our brain, not being controlled by it.]]></summary></entry></feed>