<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-15T18:08:21+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/feed.xml</id><title type="html">DakaMeditation</title><subtitle>Daka Meditation is an online meditation school. Meditation is explained and practiced.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Who is Lord Shiva?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/10/Who-is-lord-shiva.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who is Lord Shiva?" /><published>2025-01-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/10/Who-is-lord-shiva</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/daka-meditation/2025/01/10/Who-is-lord-shiva.html"><![CDATA[<p>Lord Shiva or AdiYogi is a hindu deity and member of the holy trimurti(trinity), besides Brahma and Vishnu.
It is said AdiYogi is the source of yoga. Why do I write this? Because Meditation and yoga are related.
Yoga means Unity, the unity between Atman(individual, own self) with Brahman(World Soul, universal self).
In the yogic culture it is believed that there is a coiled up snake like thing at the bottom of every humans spine.
This coiled up snake like thing is called “Kundalini”. It is the awakening of the kundalini, so it can rise up
through the seven chakras to the crown chakra, which is above the head, and cosmic consciousness is realized.
How to awaken the kundalini? Meditate daily for 20 minutes, greet the sun in the morning and bow down to it for it
spends you light and warmth.</p>
<h4 id="howto-meditate">Howto meditate?</h4>
<p>Sit in lotus posture, thumb and index are touching and resting on the knees. Observe your thoughts and let them pass
like clouds in the sky, or let them flow like water, don’t engage with them, you are not your thoughts. 
We need to learn to control our brain, not being controlled by it.</p>

<p>🕉</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lord Shiva or AdiYogi is a hindu deity and member of the holy trimurti(trinity), besides Brahma and Vishnu. It is said AdiYogi is the source of yoga. Why do I write this? Because Meditation and yoga are related. Yoga means Unity, the unity between Atman(individual, own self) with Brahman(World Soul, universal self). In the yogic culture it is believed that there is a coiled up snake like thing at the bottom of every humans spine. This coiled up snake like thing is called “Kundalini”. It is the awakening of the kundalini, so it can rise up through the seven chakras to the crown chakra, which is above the head, and cosmic consciousness is realized. How to awaken the kundalini? Meditate daily for 20 minutes, greet the sun in the morning and bow down to it for it spends you light and warmth. Howto meditate? Sit in lotus posture, thumb and index are touching and resting on the knees. Observe your thoughts and let them pass like clouds in the sky, or let them flow like water, don’t engage with them, you are not your thoughts. We need to learn to control our brain, not being controlled by it.]]></summary></entry></feed>